Guide to the Benjamin and Julia Stockton Rush Papers, 1766-1845 and undated RL.11044
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1777-1824; 1
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 8-9; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush states that he would rejoice at news of the birth of his niece if he could, but he feels as though he will never feel joy again. The mortality this day is worse than ever. He believes it is now unsafe for her to receive articles of clothing from their house. Also, he would prefer to borrow money from her brother than from a bank at the moment.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 9-10; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports that the women who waited before sending for him to treat their fever have now died. His meals are now public, and he describes his diet. He notes that some doctors have been adding bark and laudanum to his new remedies. He plans to publish to expose their ignorance.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 10-11; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports mortality is very great, and chiefly among the poor and servants. He adds that nearly 2000 people have died since the beginning of the fever. His own fever has returned and confined him to his house.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 11; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush is confined to his house, and has been prescribing based on the reports of his pupils. He remains weak, but otherwise healthy. He finds it strange when men write to propose business or contractual dealings at this point in time. Part of the final page of the letter is missing.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (n. p.), 1793 October 13-14; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush informs Julia that he has been thinking more of the children than he has in weeks and describes a dream he has had about her. He inquires after the new baby. He plans to ride out to the countryside to repair his health and later reports feeling stronger. He lists the conditions of those among their acquaintances.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 14-15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush points out that he has received no letters from Julia. He gains strength but must eat often to avoid becoming "weak and fainty." His patients now hand him a glass of milk or crust of bread as they would hand another a glass of wine. He adds that their servant, Marcus, has been very faithful and that his mother is well, but complains of the high cost of housekeeping.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 17-18; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush lists those in the neighborhood who were not his patients that have died. He praises their "black friend," Marcus, for faithfully waiting on him. He has received letters from Europe, among them a letter from Granville Sharp, authorizing him to draw on contributions in London for the African Church of Philadelphia. Among the contributors was the Duke of Grafton. Rush points out that no doctors have inquired after his health, and that their confederacy against him in stronger than ever. The letter's signature has been excised.
    Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Rush, Julia Stockton; Sharp, Granville, 1735-1813; Grafton, Augustus Henry Fitzroy, Duke of, 1735-1811; St. Thomas' Church (Philadelphia, Pa.) -- History
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 18; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush announces that Dr. Sproat has died, adding, "It is truly distressing to think of the desolation which has followed the footsteps of this man, and of all the Doctors who use Bark- Wine- Laudanum, and hot, or cold Baths in this disorder. It is much more inflammatory than a common Pleurisy, & who ever thought of using those remedies in that disease?" He notes the health of other doctors, and reports that he is now employed again by Mr. Hammond, who had been persuaded against Rush's treatment. He ends noting that Julia's sister has written to urge him to leave the city, a move he feels would be "unwise, and perhaps sinful."
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 20-21; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush details several patients' responses to treatment, or lack thereof, and includes consideration of the impact of psychological influences on recovery. He notes that the days grow colder, but they need rain. He has returned to his notes on yellow fever taken during his apprenticeship in 1762.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 October 21-22; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports that the fever declines daily and that he expects she will be able to return to the city by mid-November. He rode out for the first time in weeks, and found more people in the streets, and those more cheerful. He adds that he is feeling stronger daily.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 October 23-24; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush notes that rain and cold weather have not decreased cases of the fever; 700 have died since 11 October, and 3400 since 1 August. He feels the distress of others all the more because he cannot assist them now. He has discovered further evidence that his sister gave her life to save his. Finally, he notes that his publications are still saving lives.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 October 24; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports that his practice has fallen off. Disease has left their district and it is well known that he is too weak to see patients. His pupils attend to the poor. He describes his financial situation, then notes how few friends he now has among medical brethren, and how that impacts his future career, since he now cannot consult or operate with them.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Trenton [N.J.]), 1793 October 25-26; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush reports that only one person has been buried today in the Quaker graveyard, when 5-17 have been regular. He complains of fever treatments used by French physicians.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 27-28; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush announces he is contemplating moving into a new house before her return and considers a few locations. He adds that his day no grave was opened in the Quaker graveyard and their were no admissions or deaths in the Bush Hill hospital.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 28-29; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush has taken measures to purify their house. He points to a new clamor regarding his assertion that yellow fever has been operating in the city. He has been asked to prove that assertion.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Mrs. [Rachel] Montgomery (n. p.), 1793 October 29; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    In this letter to his sister, Rachel, Rush provides details of their sister Rebecca's death, his grief, and the state of their mother's health.
    Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 29-30; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush records a visit from physicians who have quietly sought to prove the effectiveness of his mercury treatment by using it to treat the poor. He asks Julia to join him in reading Psalm 103 and praising God for his protection. He expects to take charge of the hospital shortly.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 30-31; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush notes the health of several doctors and points out that St. Paul's Church has offered prayers twice a week since the fever began. He is not seeing patients, but is spending his time reading and making notes on the epidemic. He describes his melancholy when he contemplates the state of the city and those he has lost.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 October 31; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Rush points out that many people are returning to town; he hopes not too soon, for there are still many who are ill or dying. The rest of the letter is regarding his professional feud with Dr. Wistar over treatment for the fever. Rush is especially offended because Wistar had originally assented to the efficacy of Rush's treatment, then changed his mind.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 1; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush has discovered that a letter containing charges against him has been circulating among physicians. He plans to obtain a copy and publish it. He is inquiring after a house.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Rosehill), 1793 November 3; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush reports that he was driven to Rosehill to visit their son, Ben, and also met neighbors. He figures that two-fifths of all those sent to Bush Hill hospital have died, because his remedies were not used.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 4-5; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush outlines their full affection for each other, and makes tentative plans to visit Julia. The closing for the letter has been excised.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush challenges Julia to be patient regarding a return to town. He repeats the history of his relationship with his detractors, then returns to praising her as a "great woman" for never asking him to leave the city during the outbreak.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 8; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush reports having received various letters and items from London, including a medical book. He states that he has had no cases of yellow fever in two days. He uses the rest of the letter to recount fully his second attack of the fever, beginning October 10th. He writes that he expects her return the coming week.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 11; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush outlines the work that will keep him from visiting Julia, after all. He points out that there have been four deaths from fever, so unless there is a frost, she should not return to Philadelphia on the date they agreed upon. He repeats more of the "slander" against him.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1793 November 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Rush points out that he is too weak and busy to ride out to her at Rosehill, but she may come in to town, or he will ride out to spend the next day with her.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Dr. [Basil G.] Middleton (London), 1796 January 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 22 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Purchase, 2013
    Rush writes most likely to Dr. Basil G. Middleton, (c. 1740-1818), a former surgeon with Virginia forces in the Revolutionary War, now living in London. Rush discusses personal and medical matters, touching on College of Philadelphia medical school classes and enrollment, and comments on the unconcluded treaty with England and the American political system.
    United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Political culture -- United States; College of Philadelphia. Medical School
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Mr. Harris (n. p.), 1796 October 11; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 34 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush's copy of a letter to a Mr. Harris regarding Rush's ability to establish a patent for land in Lewistown.
    Deeds -- Pennsylvania -- Mifflin County; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 August 6; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush announces that yellow fever has broken out throughout the city, but there have been no measures yet to exterminate the disease. Their son Richard plans to move a mattress and books to their farm. Rush notes that a Mr. Thomas has left Philadelphia forever as a result of his debts, and has ruined many young men in the meantime. In a postscript, Rush points out that Capt. Mitchell of the American Army has the fever. Rush is considering leaving and is urging his patients to leave. Rush's signature has been excised.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 August 7-8; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush notes that the fever has increased more in one week than it had in three weeks in 1793 and 1797. He had made plans to leave in 7-10 days when the U. S. Mint was closed, but by the end of the letter announces more immediate plans to remove to Sydenham, which has been prepared for the family and servants. Their son John is arriving via his ship in New Castle. A note was appended to the letter in 1848, saying that the close of the letter was cut out for an autograph seeker.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 August 9-10; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 32 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush notes that John arrived, and they are now at Sydenham. He also reports that he has sold the Chapel farm for $2,500. He describes a new remedy he has developed for yellow fever. The signature has been excised from this letter.
    Yellow fever -- Treatment; Yellow Fever -- therapy; Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 August 26; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush points out that though staying in the country helps him forget all that is going on around him, he cannot forget the poor, sick, and dying in the city. Three more persons were admitted to the hospital this day than were admitted in 1793.
  - Benjamin Rush (Sydenham) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 August 31; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush notes that his pupil is better, and that he is using profuse sweating as part of his treatment for the fever. A later note was appended to the letter stating that Mrs. Rush allowed the signature to be cut away for an autograph.
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 September 27; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush reports that despite being exposed to the fever daily for two months, he is still healthy. However, he has "felt, mourned, and wept" until he could no longer do so. He reports that poor people chase him down in the street, and that he carries medicine with him in order to do all he can to help them. Free blacks and servants form a large percentage of his patients.
    Yellow fever -- Treatment; Yellow fever -- 18th century; Yellow Fever -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Yellow Fever -- Epidemiology -- Pennsylvania; Poor -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Rush, Julia Stockton
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 September 28; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 2 Leaves; 5 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush recounts all the improvements he has made for her at Sydenham. He will begin sending the family from town with the warm weather in May or June.
  - Benjamin Rush (Sydenham) letter to Nathaniel Potter (Baltimore), 1799 October 18; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush comments on commerce and the work of physicians, and on Philadelphia physicians opposed to use of mercury and bloodletting.
    Mercury; Bloodletting; Potter, Nathaniel, 1770-1843.
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) note to Julia Stockton Rush (n.p.), 1798 or 1799; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 19 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush writes a brief note to inform Julia that a friend has failed, physically.
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1798 or 1799; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush writes that deaths from fever are decreasing, and he will soon end his engagement with city hospital. He outlines activities in the family, and their preparations for her return the following week. The signature to this letter has been excised.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to unidentified, 1800 December 16; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush makes treatment recommendations for an undisclosed ailment.
    Medicine -- Practice -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia -- 18th century
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to unidentified, 1802 February 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 32 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush records the benefits of using Kinepox over variolation to inoculate against smallpox.
    Smallpox -- Vaccination; Smallpox vaccine -- History; Vaccination -- History
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to [James Currie, n. p.], 1802 March 15; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush writes a letter of introduction for University of Pennsylvania chemist, Dr. James Woodhouse.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to John Bostock (Liverpool, England), [1805 May ]; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 24 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush thanks Dr. Bostock for his essay on respiration, saying he will read it with interest and awaits Bostock's future work on the topic. The rest of the letter relates to Rush's English ancestry and friendship with Bostock's father.
    Bostock, John, 1773-1846; Rush family; Bostock, John, 1740-1774
  - Benjamin Rush (n.p.) letter to Thomas Jefferson (n. p.), 1805 June 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 20 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Copy of a letter Rush composed to Jefferson regarding appointments Jefferson has made, as well as the impact of yellow fever epidemics on commerce with Europe.
    United States -- Politics and government -- 1801-1809; Epidemics; Communicable diseases; International trade; Communicable Disease Control -- History; Disease Transmission, Infectious -- History; Yellow Fever -- History; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to John Bostock (Liverpool, England), 1806 April 7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 26 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Purchase, 1956.
    Rush thanks Bostock for his article "Analysis of Animal Fluides," then provides requested anecdotes regarding Bostock's father. Rush comments upon treatment for pulmonary consumption and the use of bloodletting in parturition and pregnancy.
    Tuberculosis -- Treatment; Bloodletting; Parturition; Pregnancy; Bostock, John, 1773-1846; Rush family; Bostock, John, 1740-1774
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) note to Julia Stockton Rush (Princeton [N.J.]), 1808 August 25; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush's brief note to his wife following her departure, enclosing 10 dollars and providing information on the family's health.
    Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Three Rivers, Canada), 1809 July 7; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush outlines how the family spent July 4th for Julia, then discusses possible successors to University of Pennsylvania chemist, James Woodhouse. Letter includes a poem by William Rush to his mother.
    Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush family; University of Pennsylvania -- Faculty
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Three Rivers, Canada), 1809 July 15; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush describes his parting with their son, James, and announces that Dr. Coxe has been appointed Professor of Chemistry. Includes a letter from Samuel Rush to his mother.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Julia Stockton Rush (Three Rivers, Canada), 1809 July 21-22; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Rush relates how he misses Julia, then describes the activities of their boys. He notes that the weather has been uncommonly cool, which has damaged crops. There has also been an outbreak of yellow fever in the city, but he expects it to be checked by the cool weather. He points out that the "ejection of Mr. Erskine's convention with our government by the British Court" has caused outrage in the city.
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Richard Henderson (Loudon Court House, Virginia), 1810 May 31; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush writes regarding a Mr. Carter's debts, particularly regarding his coffin and grave.
    Death -- Social aspects -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Burial -- Social aspects -- United States -- History -- 19th century
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to Richard Henderson (Loudon Court House, Virginia), 1810 June 27; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 32 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush writes a more detailed letter regarding Mr. Carter's debts and ill treatment of Carter, who was insane, by his family. Includes a statement of charges certified by the hospital's steward. Letter features an additional written comment made by Henderson or someone in his firm.
    Mental illness -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Mentally ill -- Treatment -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Medical care, Cost of -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to unidentified, 1810 October 20; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Rush replies to a requested consult regarding a severe case of hemorrhoids or other bowel problem. He proposes that if the patient is willing to visit Philadelphia, the problem can be treated surgically.
    Hemorrhoids; Hemorrhoids -- therapy
  - Benjamin Rush (Philadelphia) letter to W. Jones [Dr. Walter Jones] (n. p.), 1811 February 12; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; 1 Leaves; 4 pages; 26 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)